[Music]
i
spent the morning at the kremlin and its
museums
and i've never seen so many beautiful
things in my life in one day
before so to thank you
i'm going to show you my most beautiful
formula for mathematical questions
now we're going to spend the next two
hours deep on strategically
i'm i'm joking i have been
told that not everybody here is a
mathematician
so i will be showing you my favorite
equations
i'm using them as pictures to remind me
what to say
and just to rehearse the formal
structure
of the arguments this lecture
is really an invitation for us to think
about
what the brain is doing and i'm going to
take
the perspective that the brain is
optimizing something
the question is what is it optimizing so
i'm going to ask you to stem back
from psychology or machine learning
or education artificial intelligence and
just ask a simple question
what is it that we want to achieve what
quantity do we want to optimize
and i'm going to offer an answer which
is indeed
borrowed from statistical physics
from the energy but it has a very
different meaning and interpretation for
others and so what i want to do is to
walk through
the interpretations and the meanings
from the psychological
cognitive and sentient perspective
um further to that if
we understand the mathematical
principles
of higher brain function or indeed just
perceptions and action
then it should be possible to shine a
new light
on message passing in the brain of the
aeronal dynamics
on the anatomy of the grade the
functional anatomy called the
computational anatomy
so much of my lecture will be in trying
to
rehearse the general idea in some of
that
terms but illustrating how
far one can take the formal principles
in understanding the empirical brave
responses that a lot of us measure
say for example the eugene
electric magnetic brain responses or
indeed
just our choices and our decisions on
our behavior
so the agenda is ambitious i'm going to
address a very deep and bigger question
of what
do our brains do i provide a potential
answer
but use the answer to illustrate to you
how
far i can get in stimulating or
understanding
quite high level of sophisticated
behaviors and i wanted
to eventually end with an example of
reading and language understanding and
its brain response currents so that's
where we're going to try and go
if i take too long you're going to stop
me
and then we'll have a conversation which
is usually the best part of these
sections
of questions and answers so i'm not
going to talk for more than the
and hour i look forward to having a
conversation
about some of these locations now have
you all read this
i will be asking questions
this is what we're going to be talking
about i'm going to
introduce um the question at hand
and then provide this answer in terms
of something called active inference
closely related to things like active
learning machine learning or active
vision
in the visual sciences this is putting
perception in an inactive
context that we are actively perceiving
and we
are in charge of the way that we
palpate or sample the world in order
to optimize our perceptual synthesis
i'm going to show that mathematically
that's just the same
as gathering evidence for one's own
existence
and now i've explained that connection
in about five or six months all of this
self-evidencing this active perception
this active inference
rests upon predicting
worlds actively having a model
of how the world works and how the world
supplies our sensory organs
with sensations and stimulation
on thermal outcomes and that's known as
a generative model
a model that generates sensory
consequences
from the causes out there which we want
to understand so i'm going to spend some
time illustrating
the kinds of genetic models that we use
to simulate behaviors either in animal
studies
or in economic gains and
the resulting or ensuing
belief updating that we can then look at
as if we were
electrophysiologists or brain matters
and that's from the principles to the
process today
so making a distinction between the
principles
that we're going to be talking about
active influence and self-evidence
to the neuronal processes that are
occurring in your head
at the moment that we can measure as
neuroscientists
and cultivate scientists i'll
briefly rehearse some empirical
predictions i'll go through this quite
quickly because i want to get to the end
which is
some of the most advanced applications
of these ideas to understanding
functional architectures of the brain
and that's the use of deep
generative models that have a deep
hierarchical structure
both in terms of abstraction but also
in terms of time exactly the sort of
models you would need
to generate language and i'm going to
turn that on its head by saying these
are the models
that we use to understand language and
they're going to
present some very simple simulations of
reading
and show that they produce the same
electrophysiological responses that we
use in classical paradigms like the
smashing negativity
or p300 paradigm so let me just start
very abstractly and very simply
imagine you are an adult you are a bird
of prey and you're hungry
so what are you going to do
[Music]
what are you going to do
search perfect in that one
simple answer search there
is a whole range of hidden truths
about what we are trying to optimize
so here's the owl searching and there's
the unhappy
prey he's about to eat by the searching
owl
so clearly if i'm hungry the first thing
i'm going to do
is to resolve my uncertainty
about where the prey exists where
here the mouse exists and it's that
notion of searching resolving
uncertainty
that underwrites everything i'm going to
talk about
for the next 50 minutes
it's important because there are two
ways you can write down
and here are the first of the formulas
but i repeat
please do not worry about the maths
they're just here to remind me
about different ways of thinking about
things that you can write down in
computer code
or indeed mathematically there are two
ways you can write down
the objectives for living
from the power of you or for me
first of all we could write down an
expression
for things that we do controlled
variables
in engineering which we'll call you at
this point in time
as um maximizing
the value of some states of the world
if i did that thing
and then what i would be able to do is
to create a policy pie
that for any given current state if i
apply this
action i will move to the net state and
then i will maximize
the value of being in that next step
so this is the notion of
a value function of states giving rise
to a state action policy
it requires you to believe in and commit
to
the idea that for every state
there is a label which tells you how
valuable that straight is
and then all you have to do is to choose
the action that takes you from this
state
to the most valuable state
but that's not going to work to explain
searching
for the simple reason that it's
is all about reducing uncertainty
then we know immediately because
uncertainty
is an attribute of a belief it's not an
attribute of
a thing it's an attribute of the belief
about
something then the function that we need
to optimize
has to be a function of a belief and if
the belief is about something then
that's
a function of a function of something
mathematically that's called a function
so what we actually need
what the alternative way of doing this
is our
best action at this point in time
maximizes a function of beliefs
about states and plans states in the
world
if i did this action here
and i'm going to describe this belief in
terms
of probability through scarier
probabilities
over different states again don't worry
about the math just remember
the queue is a probabilistic belief
furthermore the notion of searching
tells you something else very important
it means that it
matters whether i search for my phrase
and then i eat it or i try
which means that you can't just write
down an objective function
as a function of beliefs you have to
define a policy which is a sequence of
actions in a particular order so now
what we have
is a notion that there is a best policy
that entails or
a sequence of actions in a particular
order
and in machine learning or controlled
theories and
sequential concept translation for us
all it means is we know
that the best kind of um
policy defined style and it maximizes
the sum of this functional and i'll say
now this is the free energy
function of elites to give them that
so these two contrasting ways
of writing down formally what things
do what living things
emerge in many different guises in many
different contexts so
the notion that you can explain behavior
in terms of optimizing your value
function that's the problem
technology principle from this
you'll find lots of examples optimal
control theory
dynamic programming deep reinforcement
learning
especially utility theory and economics
apple's induction
and so on
the other approach which is the approach
that we are going to
pursue is based upon
the principle of least action so action
here
is just basically a time integral
or a time average of an energy and i've
just said
efforts of free energy so this path
is an action and we're going to maximize
that action
so that we choose the optimum action
and this is the energy principle also
known as active inference
from this we will hopefully can
speculate along artificial curiosity
um an intrinsic motivation in robotics
emerges
we can also cast this in terms of basic
decision theory
as i mentioned before this is
an aspect of sequential policy
optimization
now i've deliberately sort of contrasted
classical value function with three
energy functionals
to highlight the foundation these
approaches are belief-based
and these are not but i'd actually show
that they come
up together again so this
becomes this when we remove uncertainty
so i'll try
to start bringing back to expectations
and theory
in a few slides but for the moment
let's just focus on what this quantity
begins and i'm going to give you one
answer
and i'm not going to motivate if there
is a deeper back story here
from statistical physics and basic
mechanics
but i'm not going to worry about it i'm
just going to tell you what it is
and then hopefully convince you it is a
suitable objective function
by a series of examples which will be
less useful
so here's the basic idea this quantity
is known as a variation
it's a information theoretical quantity
quite closely related to something
invented here congrats
complexity or multiple complexity
it's also known as an attendance low
bandwidth machine learning
in statistics it's known as blog model
evidence
also known as marginal likelihood
is it's a very very important quantity
which you see
in nearly every field the fact that it's
called
basic moral evidence um
give me a license to describe this
optimization of self-evidence and i will
see
why that works from a statistician's
point of view
this negative physical free energy here
this negative evidence and not evidence
of
evidence lower bound elbow and machine
learning
um is just the probability of getting
these
observations own
at this point in time given a model
of how these outcomes were generated and
i am going to beat that one
from a statistician's point of view you
can always
write this quantity this evidence
as complexity as negative
uh evidence as complexity minus accuracy
or log evidence minus complexity
what that means is we're going to
consider the brain
as a statistical organ an organ that's
trying to make
inferences just in exactly the same way
that you would scientists
try to make inferences about differences
between one group and another group
using a t statistical and analysis of
covariance
the brain is doing exactly the same
thing with its sensual data
it's trying to test different hypotheses
different beliefs about
how those sensory data were caused
and it's doing so by maximizing the
negative moral evidence
which means that it is trying to find
the simplest minimally complex
explanation that provides an
accurate account of the sensory data
and that's going to be very important in
the complexity particles are very
important
so it's not just finding an accurate
account of data
it has to be personalized and simple
in a sense so
this variation free energy is just the
mathematical
expression of this mixture of complexity
and accuracy and we imagine the brain
just
organizes learns infers passes messages
all in the service of minimizing
its complexity minus accuracy or
maximizing legacy minimizing different
complexities
and if that were at the end then that
would be a perfectly suitable
and formal account intersection but what
we're seeing here
is how the brain comes back and actively
samples
the data that he could use to infer
the causal structure in the outside
world
and that's a really interesting part
so we've already said that we have to
define the problem in terms of sequences
of actions and policies
and what we're going to say is that
we're going to select
those policies that will maximize
the expected free energy
after performing that sequence of
behaviors
so what that means is we're going to
effectively
choose policies that minimize
complexity expected following
an action and minimize accuracy
sorry maximize accuracy following an
action
but notice now the outcomes
are now random variables that they
haven't yet occurred
they are in the future so now we have to
take an average
over things that could happen in the
future
so now we're talking about the average
complexity and that turns out to be risk
risk and this is where the greatest
reminds me to provide the formal
definition
so risks it really believes about what
will happen
if i pursue this policy
compared to what a priority i prefer
so i'll say that again risk is the
divergence or the difference
between what i think will happen if i do
this
and what i prefer a priority to happen
so here my beliefs about the sorts of
outcomes that i encounter
define the sorts of outcomes
that i expect to experience i've been
rich
happy warm having my temperature within
the physiological range
all the things are making me and they're
good and a happy me
they are like a priori by prior
beliefs about the outcomes that i will
attain
if i could see this policy and the
goodness of the policy
corresponds to the minimum wage
reducing the difference between what i
think is going to happen
and like my preferences mathematically
that's called risk
and we'll see another instance of that
from that economic perspective in a
moment
at the same time i'm going to maximize
my expected accuracy
so what would that look like what does
the expected accuracy look um
like if i haven't actually got the
observations at hand
well what it means is i am going to
differently choose concepts that make
the sensory data as unambiguous as
possible
so for example if i walk into a dark
room
i'm going to turn the light off because
that's a policy
which means that i can unambiguously
to reduce the uncertainty about what
would be causing those sensory
impressions
there's a table in front of me that's
enlightened over there
that i would not be able to see in an
unparticular sensory context
so this is a little bit about like the
joke about the man who is drunk
and is searching for his kids and his
searching chris cleans under the life
post or the streetlight
and someone else said what are you doing
i am searching for my keys did you drop
them there
no i dropped them over there so why is
searching here
because i can't see over there that's a
perfectly
based optional response and it reflects
the fact that we were
part of the drives for our good policies
and those which minimize ambiguity or
maximize
expected agency and then once we've
found a good policy
or sound action from that the actual
change in states in the world down there
beyond that sensory
blanket and that will then supply new
observations and then we'll redo
our perceptual synthesis again um
finally simplest hacking explanation
what's going on
use our beliefs about states of the
world to run out and simulate
another future another policy select the
policy
that minimizes the risk of ambiguity
select the action
and so the perception action or the
action perception
cycle continues on and on and on
all in the service of minimizing
risk of an ambiguity minimizing
expected surprise or
negative free energy which is just
uncertainty
in physics but you can remember this is
putting these two things together it's
just
minimizing uncertainty about the future
where that uncertainty includes
preferences that i feel familiar with
so that's the basic story in terms of
what is this functional of beliefs that
we want to optimize
and this is a horrible slide if you
don't do maths but
again please ignore these questions i
just wanted to show you how easy it
is to take away from these equations
and end up with a formalism that
people have been working with for
centuries or at least decades and
decades
so if you are a mathematician or a
physicist
you will now recognize where why
this quantity is called free energy it's
basically
an expected native uh a lot of
probability here which is called an
entropy
um and then this quantity if i put them
together energy so it's basically the
difference between
an energy and an entropy so it's the
energy level
to do work hence free energy but just by
shifting these things around or grouping
them together in a different way
we can interpret it in terms of capacity
and accuracy as we've just described
so all i'm saying here is that there are
different ways of interpreting these
monitors depending upon the words that
you use the constructs
you know taught and you use in
conversation with your colleagues
they're all equally viable another nice
example of just
switching things around here just over
here this over here
means there's another interpretation of
splitting this uncertainty
minimizing capacity of good policies or
expecting the energy g
here we can actually carve it or
decompose it into another
pair of quantities called epistemic
volume
and expected value so let me show you
how that works
more precisely let me show you how
people have already been using
these constructs these quantities in
their work before
if you just focus on these two terms
here
what this corresponds to is essentially
the expected difference
between beliefs about what's going on
out there
if i had some observation
in the future relative to the beliefs
about
state of the world without those
observations
so what that means is this
corresponds to the salience of
the policy or the action it tells me the
amount of uncertainty i am reducing
or the amount of information i have
gained
if i looked over there as opposed to
looking over here
so this quantity has been used a lot in
digital neuroscience to understand
visual searches and sailing stats in
terms of
the best place to go and sample the
world from
it's the place that minimizes your
uncertainty or maximizes your
information again
that has savings or epistemic
performance
it's also mathematically exactly the
same as the mutual information
or the mutual predictability or the
shared variance
between the causes states of the world
and the consequences the outcomes that
are generated by those states
so effectively what we're trying to do
is to move
palpate our world have a visually with
eye movements
literally with our skin receptors by
between
for example the layout of
a new hotel room in the dark you're
testing hypotheses
you're feeding your way around you're
sampling actively
those sensations that tell you ah
no this is a table not a bed but you
have to have those hypotheses
in mind in order to reach reaches of
uncertainty
over the hypotheses that you are
entertaining
and in doing that you are increasing the
mutual information between
what you feel and what caused those
feelings
so that's a very important aspect of
this um
uncertainty reducing imperative this
free energy function of beliefs
um let's make things a little bit
simpler so now
i'm doing my comments before i'm gonna
get back to the value function
but if you remember before i said the
difference between the valid function
and the free energy functional is that
one is belief based
and the other is not i can actually
convert the
scheme into a value-based scheme by
removing uncertainty
so the first circumstance
is basically ambiguity i'm going to
assume there are creatures out there
that can see
every hidden state of the world there's
no sensory noise there are no
hidden states in the world and what i
see is my sensory organs
my observations my boundaries are the
states
and what we are left with
is just the divergence of the difference
between the predicted and preferred
outcomes it's just our risk
so this is risk sensitive control in
economics
also known as kl on control because this
is a a klr called
divergence uh so in optical control
theory this is done scale control
economics with
sensitive control
what it tells us is that this risk
is basically what is left if we remove
ambiguity
but let's make the final move and
actually take away ambiguity
so now not only um sorry let's make the
final movement take away the risk
having taken away from the ambiguity so
by taking away the risk what i'm saying
is that i am equally uncertain
what will happen if i do that in the
future and if i take that
away we end up with just this term
here so i'll remove this now and now i'm
just left with this so what is this well
it's just
expected utility so this is what
economists use
to score the probability of choosing
this positive policy in the absence
of differential uncertainty both in
terms of ambiguity but also
in terms of risk there's a deep history
uh to the exception to their utility
specific value both in economics and of
course in
and reinforcement based on exactly the
same
idea and some reward loss function
uh that can ignore uncertainty and then
you will see
policy of action selection being
completely described
by this value function so
the purpose of that was really to
illustrate
how in general
belief-based formulation of
the thing that we are trying to optimize
mainly manchester united evidence based
on model evidence for our models of the
world
or minimize our uncertainty to active
palpation of that world
and are generalizations and things that
we have all been working with for
possible attention but you when you get
to these special cases
if you remove uncertainty so that the
belief aspect triggers now
to the point if we talk about value
functions
just to make it very clear for those
people
who haven't come across information gain
or epistemic value before i just want to
give you an intuitive example
of what it means to reduce to tunes
actions and dissolve uncertainty even
before you know
what's going to happen so imagine you're
driving a car
and you are looking around
in the night time and you don't have a
chance
you're stopped at a traffic light and
there is a filter on this traffic light
it could be pointing right
or left and you can choose to either
look over here
or you can choose to look exactly at the
side
now if you're wondering about driving
you're going to have a 50 50
believe posterior belief or private
leave before looking
at over here but the sign is pointing
to the left or to the right and if you
look over here
then you're not going to change that
posterior belief
so it doesn't matter whether the side is
pointing to the right or to the left
looking over here won't resolve
any uncertainty you will have a 50-50
posterior belief whether the sign is
pointing this direction
or in that direction so this is an
example
of a policy that has no epistemic value
at all
contrast that with a situation
where you're looking directly at the
sign and resolving your ambiguity
and getting very precise sensory
information so now
if the side is pointing in this
direction then you will be 100
certain point in this direction if the
side is pointing in this direction
then you will be 100 certain it's
pointing in that direction
and you know that and you've known that
before you
even made an eye movement so that's
basically
what this chaos divergence this
epistemic performance this salience
um
[Music]
what the best move is to
fundamental imperative epistemic
imperative uncertainty reducing
self-evidence so
that's all the hard work done now i'm
just going to see some pretty examples
uh and simulations to show what it looks
like
in simulations and hopefully convince
you that you've seen
a lot of this feminine biology in papers
indeed possibly
in your opponent research i should say
you know i made a joke about the
mathematics and the formula
before and perhaps i should
excuse why we use the mathematics so
much
there's a simple reason that if you
really want to understand something
that's richard finally so you have to be
able to build one
and to be able to build a little
creature that does the paradise that we
ask our subjects
or our experimental animals to do
you need to be able to write down the
song and you need to be able to write
down
the mathematical formula upon which the
software
are generated so that's our motivation
it's really to create little
silicone in silicon creatures
that we can expose to the same
experimental paradigms or legions
as real creatures and then see what
this belief updated this active infant
self tendency looks like
and then we'll see if we can see the
same kind
of empirical criminology in real
creatures
so that's the excuse or the motivation
for it
but it does require you to commit to
very particular
and well specified morals
of that are used by
creatures living systems and explain
their paradigm or their world and a very
general one
again please ignore the questions we're
going to walk you through with the
graphics
on the moral um is called a mark of
decision process
so with this single and same model
we have modeled an entire range of
different kinds of behavior
ranging from
curiosity and problem solving so
many different kinds of paradigms can be
modeled with this one very general
generative model so i'm just going to
briefly take you through to give you one
worked example
just to give you a feel for the
simplicity in case in
your future work you want to use these
kinds of models to simulate your
paradigms
so the idea is we need to generate
outcomes things that can be of a
creature
or something like me would be able to
also
see hear feel and these outcomes
we're going to say are going to be
generated by hidden states of the world
they are hidden because they are not
directly observable
we can only observe our sensations
we can't see directly the causes of
those sensations so they're
often referred to as either latent or
hidden states
and they have a narrative they have
dynamics
there are successions and transitions
off in states so if i'm in
a particular state at this point in time
i will be
promising this state next point in time
and so on and so forth
so we have this cascade of hidden states
each day generating an outcome
as time ticks along and the mapping
between
the hidden states and the outcome is
just a life economic it's a probability
of getting
this outcome given this particular state
of the world
that's usually by an eight matrix
now clearly the way that the world
unfolds
these hidden states depends upon how i
have to plot
it matters you know the hidden state of
where my eye is pointing
determines what i actually see
so we imagine that some states of the
world depend upon
policies in other words the transitions
between this state of the world in the
next into the world
at the next time encoded by probability
transition matrix b
is a function of policy and we've just
said that policies
are determined by our prior preferences
um and to ensure that the prior
parentheses by c
cost function and they will have some
precision so confidence associated now
we've all encountered that gamma i won't
talk about that very much but it is
interesting because it looks
very much like dopamine responses in
your brain
and i'll show you a brief example of
that later and finally
i just have to specify beliefs about the
initial states
of the initial states and a few hyper
parameters
that statistically privatize it and with
that
model i can model
um furthermore if i make some
simplifying assumptions
about my beliefs about all the unknowns
the key unknowns of course being
the hidden states of the world
generating outcomes
and crucially the confidence so these
are the two things i need
to infer full good beliefs about by
minimizing
that by optimizing that free energy
or that energy about
i'm also going to think about optimizing
the confidence of my policies
but the important thing here notice
the recasting behavior here
in terms of forming beliefs about what i
could do
and then just selecting action from the
most likely
or the policy that i think happens
likely to be perceived at the moment
it's sometimes sometimes known as
planning as influence
so it's casting action
as a process of inference
so you actually if you subscribe to this
formulation
the choice on the selection of what to
do next
is an active difference it's inferring
this is the most likely thing that
somebody think
something like he would do in this
belief state
so i'm going to be trying to involve
that kind of uncertainty over the
workforce
or preferences and you can write all of
these uh particular privatizations
if you then just uh apply
something that this is called a mean
field approximation
uh just parameterize these beliefs with
but from my perspective the results are
remarkably simple
and more importantly look very very
similar
to the dynamics and believe update as
you have
been seen in simplified versions of
breakfast
so remember before i said there are just
three things we don't know in this long
state of the world the policies pie
and the precision or confidence placed
with those policies
and it turns out that the solutions
that optimize that free energy function
can be expressed here as a non-linear
function
of linear mixtures of beliefs about the
past and future
and observations now and this starts to
look very much like a very simple neural
network model
a sigmoidifying activation function
operating
on linear mixtures of activities
elsewhere in the brain
a very very simple expression
that now starts to provide a metaphor
for neuronal responses
about the past in the future so written
into this
giant model is an elemental form of
memory
and prospection post-fiction and
prediction
memory for the past and the future so
there's a sense of
time and progression implicit
in this update if we look
at policy selection it's simply a soft
class function
of this expected free energy not the
goodness of a policy
and this is the classic softness
response rule
used in economics and much of
reinforcement learning
interestingly the confidence one over
gamma
here um looks as though it's updated
according to
something that's very similar to a
reward prediction there which takes us
off
in a very different direction in the
direction of dopamine and the
relationship with
reward predictions but i want to move on
to
different parameters with this one
itself
again it's very nice because with the
update rules and
solutions that optimize this free energy
functional
look exactly like that so you have these
functions that have associated here
calcium this is the d one but if we were
looking at the a1 we see the
outcomes and the states coming together
as a product
an and we just accumulate evidence by
building
uh connection strengths that then decay
again
as a function of time and then finally
we have our action selection here
and with these very simple rules you can
start to
engineer or propose a very crude
or coarse functional anatomy
observations come in say
visual quartets they are used
to update beliefs about states in the
world
hit the campus at the time these beliefs
were then used
to evaluate the goodness of the policy
in terms of the expected free energy
and ambiguity um in
the front past the brexit basal gangular
corticothalamic um uh loops
um where the confidence in his pulses
may be mediated by sodium
eventually technical area and that
nature around the next action
that changes the world the world gives
you gives you the next
observation and so the cycle continues
they're very true that relatively simple
understanding of the
computational mastery that you get to so
here's
and i'll close down with two examples
one very simple example of origin
in a maze and then we'll come to um
a brief survey of advances in
models of this sort of happy meals
trying to start things like
language comprehension and reading so
this is
an example i don't i don't need to go
through it in detail
in brief what we have is a little rat
our house in the teammates and
it lights rewards and it's got two moons
it can make
two moons and it doesn't know whether
the reward is on the right
or on the left what it also knows though
is that there is an instructional cue
at the bottom arm of the maze that tells
him
whether the reward is on the left or the
right
so that presents an interesting choice
for this place
it can go to one part and once it goes
through one of the two rewarding ones it
has to stay there
which means that it can go there and get
two rewards
on 50 cents at a time where he can go
there and get nothing
on 15 of the time or he can go down here
and to find out whether reward is and
then get
with 100 probability the reward for half
the time
so the expected value is exactly the
same
but by going to the instructional theory
you can immediately reduce the expanding
which means that if this mass was
minimizing
its uh it was optimizing its expected
free energy of minimizing its it should
go if we simulate those equations on the
previous slide
with the generative model which i've
written down here to the appropriate for
this
paradigm it should go and get the extent
and then go and get its reward and
indeed that's what it does so
it starts off what i'm showing here is
behavior
over 32 trials in terms
of where the reward was it was on the
left or the right and the policy that he
chose
the outcome the amount of reward
and beliefs about whether the reward is
on the right or the left
in terms of the additional steps what
i've done here
is after switching the reward up to the
first
couple of presentations i then left the
reward
on the left hand side and i want to see
what's going to happen
so initially as we might anticipate
the mass goes and finds the epistemic
view resolves with
uncertainty about what to do and then
indulges
in its risk behavior
so then chooses the pragmatic
preferred option by going straight to
the reward
and is as happy as it could be
however as time goes on it now learns
that in fact reward is over there all
the time
so now the energetic value of that
instructional cue gets less
and less and less it's resolving less
and less uncertainty
because it's increasingly certain that
the reward
is on the left-hand side due to its
experience potential learning
learning about these initial states
through evidence accumulation
under heavier style plasticity so at one
point
it changes its preferred policy and
jumps to a pragmatic
explosive policy so we've got this
natural
progression from exploration
to exploitation that is purely
a reflection of the fact that we are
using a belief-based
functional because the goodness
or the thing to choose depends upon my
beliefs and my uncertainty
whether i need to write that so to your
answer search
it depends upon the need for search and
that costs like a very familiarism
environment there isn't enough
um this line just summarizes that and
it's exactly the same point that
so basically learning underwrites
confident policy selection and that
confidence is reflected
in this precision parameter which was so
much longer
trial updates of this parameter here it
looks almost exactly like deadly
we can also look at the simulations of
these updates
during a particular trial so it seemed
it makes a move that sees this
makes another move because as soon as it
sees anything
it has to iterate these equations in
order
to find the day's optimal solution
the self-evidence observation and that
looks a lot like the bench-related
potential
physiological uh research and
interesting what happens is
there's less belief updating when
it's more familiar and confident about
the environment you can get an
attenuation
of these responses but an increase
in the confidence because it knows
exactly what's going to happen
and indeed what it expects to happen
does indeed happen
and it goes and it starts its knowledge
about where
the reward is
so using magic for example you can tell
all sorts of stories
you can tell a story about the
representation of the future in the past
so
this is the beginning of the trial the
first second move
and of course as these beliefs are
updated
what are beliefs about the future
consequences of action
now become the memories of outcasts
there's an interesting shift of time and
title frames of reference that means
things like
what's predictions become post pictures
that comes very interesting when you
accumulate the from a child to child
it also allows you to think about
the approach responses to the things
that you would ultimately try to choose
as opposed to things that you are not
going to choose
a nice literature in the empirical
papers showing exactly this form of
saltation divergence
as time progresses in terms of selective
responses
shown by these expectation encoded
simulated
europa neural populations that mirrors
or reflects
exactly the empirical results
and we can even plot these responses as
a function of where
the mouse is and what it emerges from
this kind of architecture
are place things place cells
that sometimes are very unambiguous for
example
the two rewarding locations sometimes a
little bit more
ambitious we can also perform simulated
onboard experiments with this much
negativity experiments
so these are the same results i showed
you before
but i'm now telling a different story
about them using a different language
as if i were an electrophysiologist
doing
bubble paradigms so what i'm going to do
when is is allowed sees the same
stimulus
when he's familiar with it and when he's
not familiar with it
it does the same response selects the
same policy
so the only thing that's different
between the perception of the action
is its beliefs that it has accumulated
through experience
and if i associate this with a standard
stimulus and this was a
normal or normal stimulus
and indeed we can reproduce the
phenology
of this much negativity do the same
thing with those
simulated green responses and show a
classical phenomena
in single unit in metrophysiology in
dopamine
cells may be a transfer of phasing
responses
from the rewarding view the
unconditioned stimulus
to the instruction like islamic key
which you can think of here
as the conditioned students so again
nothing's changing the other that i've
told a slightly different story about
the results that emerge from this
simulated rat
and all of them lend a degree of
conscious validity
to its overall thesis that everything
is in service of self-evidencing
maximizing evidence to my joint model of
the world
and selecting actions that minimize
uncertainty namely this
ambiguity so i'm going to finish now
with a very quick
run through of exactly the same
technology and ideas that apply to
slightly sophisticated
genetic models or the soul that people
might use
to understand language and generate
language
now i like this graphic
it's a nice graphic because once you've
written down formally
what you think is driving message
passing belief updating and behavior
you can now just extend that formalism
by generalizing it to hierarchical
structures
and when you do that you start to see
lots of emerging behaviors that now look
a lot more like
the kind of behaviors that psychologists
study
in human beings so what we've done here
is
taking our standard little mdp model
states kicking over time one times two
generating through the likelihood matrix
and outcome here
in transitions encountered by the b
matrix
depend on some points as pi that itself
that are informed by the expected free
energy gene equivalence of those pulses
what we've done is put another one of
these on top
crucially it operates at a slower time
scale
so the amp comes from
the process at the higher hierarchical
level
now cause things that don't change on a
faster time scale
there are lots of things we could have
chosen we could determine
the likelihood of matrices where we
could have chosen the likelihood of a
particular policy
we've actually chosen here just the
initial state
it really means that the outcomes from
the journey model's point of view
of the higher level are in play
for the duration of the state
transitions at the lower level
and you can imagine you're putting a
faster level than this and a faster and
faster one so you're writing in
you're baking in to your generative
model
not only by high level depth of
outstretching
but also a deep diaphragm
on time depth a separation of temporal
scales
over time and of course that's what we
need to understand
language you know i would have a
representation
of a sentence a phrase one level
and that's the same sentence of phrase
from the beginning of the first
phoneme to the end of the last 20 it's
the same object
but i've passed the time skill that this
current word
will change but this current word is the
same word
from the beginning of the words first
time frequency glide phoning possibly to
the last one
as we keep going lower and lower and
lower we now generate faster and faster
dynamics
using this kind of model so you may be
asking and that's all
this these equations say that they're
just a higher up in generalization
of the first level we use the rat into
this deep dichronic structure this is
exactly the same model
and the reason i show this and the
reason i like this model
is you can generate this graph
automatically from this graph and this
graph is known as a factor graph
now it may not mean very much to
psychologists
but if you're a computer scientist and
you want
to design the message capacity in the
most efficient way
this is the design so
what was saying here are what this
figure
says if you can write down the form of
your generative markers
you have automatically written down
the message passing graph and at some
level
a brain must be used in terms of
connections
and passing messages over these
for those of you who are interested
these photographs
are interesting because they place the
variables on the edges
and the probability distributions at the
nodes
that's why they're called fraction
graphs so the probability distributions
are
the factors of identity of the marginals
you can forget that if it wasn't
interesting what is interesting to
remember is you can generate these
things automatically
and once you've done that you can start
to make little brains
in software that could actually be
animal
systems or very large scale silica
integrated chips for example or
classical uh computers during computers
anyway so once you bring
down the factory graph and you learn the
architecture of the message passing you
can actually go to the neural network
and ask where are the isomorphisms in
terms of the structure
of the dynamics the temporal scheduling
of those
messengers in real brains
and it's an interesting jigsaw problem
to solve
but there are lots of immediate
parallels that become evident when you
just look at the fact about love
and you look at the textbook
neurologically i just sketched out
some ideas here we don't need to talk
about this the point
is that there's a very interesting
opportunity
once you understand what has to be the
computational anatomy
if you commit to this genitive model
approach and
self-evidence and formulation of belief
updating behavior
if you commit to that then you've got
that necessary
computation lately you've got the
empirical neural anatomy
that we presume does this computation so
now you can start to look for parallels
and assign different roles to different
parts of the brain so for example
in this instance it looks as if the
goodness paradigm contains labels for
policies for example just on the basis
of the
connectivity in reference to that
photograph of the previous stage
but let me finish that just by taking
you through conceptually
a journey model of a simulated
agent is doing a very simple form of
pictographic reading
so here there are no letters but there
are little icons
and the position of these icons
defends a particular word so
an icon can be that comprises each word
if you like comprises two icons there
could be seeds
a bird or a cat and if
the cat is next to the bird that means
the bird will flee so that's the word
flea if the seeds are linked to a bird
that means the word feed where it can
feed
on the thumb on the seats
if however there's nothing next to
the bird so the seats are down here from
the diagonal corner
that just means weight so it's a very
simple little language that we've
you know we've arbitrarily invented
um and the reason
for using this pictographic
form is that the agent has to decide
where to look
if he wants to read this word look at
the letters
in the word it has to decide where to
look at i
can look over here over here over here
over here
as it denoted by the locations one two
three and four
from the point of view of the geometry
model what does that mean
these are the states the hidden states
that you would need
to generate an outcome so what would be
essentially
a sensory outcome would be feeding the
diet looking
at positions one two three or four or
what i'm actually sampling or phone
creating a time
which can either do nothing seeds
a bird or a cat but to generate those
outcomes i have to know
the configuration of these
pictographic letters where i
am looking and i've introduced another
hidden straight here which is flipping
really like presenting words
in upper or lowercase so with those
three causes i can generate
any particular outcome in a visual
modality
and a pre-receptive or feeling where i
am currently
pointing my eyes modality
and because i have written down the
generative model
i can use that standard message passing
scheme of the previous slide to simulate
inference
i can simulate what this sort of
creature would do
in terms of foraging for information by
trying to understand what word it is
looking at
but what i really want to do is to do
that with some deep
technical structure some diachronic
aspect i wanted to actually
remember the words and see and
from the point of view magenta model
generates sentences or sequences of
words
from the point of view of
self-evidencing
inverting magenta law to recognize
what this word is in the context of
beliefs about what sentences
so to do that i now have to put together
four words or four different pages if
you like
and these four words are basically
sequences of these
three words here typically 50 percent
three point feet uh classify those with
an even higher
level which we actually didn't have
nothing to show here
so now if i know the sentence i don't
sequence one
you know three-way feed point and i know
where we are in terms of which page
we're looking at
i can now generate the word and generate
uh the word if i have now regular
information about where i am looking and
whether i flip it or not
i can now generate the outcome and if i
can generate the outcome
that means i can invert the outcomes to
make inferences and have beliefs
about the sentence so i'm going to take
that factor graph that computational
activity
and this generated model and then
simulate reading
in terms of where this agent looks
to try and accumulate heavens and build
posterior beliefs about the sentence
in his reading and the actual sentence
that is reading
is three weight feed weight
and these are the expectations
of the lowest level about what is
actually there at the lowest level
and the key point made in these
simulations
is you can have very precise beliefs
about what you would see if you looked
over there
even though you never actually looked at
them
and these precise beliefs come from this
deep structure
so for example you can see
that
to the second word at no point
because they actually sample a stimulus
that is either seeds
or birds it sees nothing on either
sample
and yet he knows because he knows what
could
possibly happen in terms of the
alternative structure
of the sentence then the solution has to
be
seen up here and birds up here and
indeed it's posterior
elite is hallucinating effectively in a
very positive and basical way
the existence of these persons
even though he never looked there and
you see evidence of that
if you look in detail at this sequence
of
eye movements as they form beliefs
they dissolve uncertainty they respond
to anesthetic affordance
and go and get the next sort of
information
that will resolve uncertainty about what
this agent is looking at
i share the same results here in a
different format just to emphasize
the separation of temple scales
so these are beliefs
at the higher level about one or six
sentences
that this synthetic agent
was looking at i notice uh it's only
right at the end
it actually resolves it's uncertainty
about the sentence because
these three sentences share everything
apart from the last word
so in no glass immediately you must be
looking around these two sentences
because the first first word
is unique to these three sentences but
the last word
is ambiguous so this uncertainty
evolves slowly and is maintained slowly
to his only result
by the last word in contrast
the beliefs about what particular word i
am currently looking at
develop much much more quickly so these
converge to a particular
posterior belief and then
that is evidence for the higher
sentence-based belief
and then we start here as we can get a
new outcome the value outcome
different visual impressions and i try
to indicate that in terms of
this separation of temple time scales
dictated by and only by
the belief updating i just want to make
a point the point again
that what you actually see in these
in cynical creatures is very similar to
what you see
as an electrophysiologist so for example
pre-circadian delicate activity in the
prefrontal cortex
shown here in elastic format
looks very similar to the kind of
responses that observe some of the
recordings shown here in terms
of a bar chart furthermore if we look at
the deflections associated with the
brief updating
on a stimulus by stimulus basis we've
seen something that looks very much
like the peripheral evoked potentials
during antivision in markets and i just
want to close by pursuing that
by focusing on the responses to stimuli
towards the end of the sentence and i'm
going to play a trick
on this little creature i'm going to
introduce a violation
two violations of a different sort in
the home
while reproducing canonical responses
inclined in common neuroscience namely
a pre-attended like this much negativity
at about 100 270 milliseconds
and then a reorienting novelty-like
response a later
more endogenous response sometimes
referred to as a
p300 associated with somali violations
by changing stimuli so there's a
surprising
meaning to the word so i'm going to do
that just by
presenting it in uppercase i'm going to
present it in lowercase
so this is if you like the steepness
inclination at the low level
and i've shown the results of the low
level in blue
without the um manipulation
and then plotting the difference here
maybe it looks very much like
this much negativity
[Music]
if i now do the same shape at this time
instead of just changing
uppercase to lowercase i now actually
change the meaning of the word
but use the same stimuli i know i've got
a much more semantic
high level violation and now the thing
that recognizes the surprise
of the free energy
here is first but also now
the second semantic level but of course
it's had to wait longer
to get the evidence from the first level
to be surprised
to do with belief updating to respond to
that surprise which means that
the difference waveforms are now
expressed in the
peristine this time in a regime that
would correspond to the p300
so it's a very particular specific
example
but i use this just to mention how far
you can get
an understanding of classical results
that are used
and have been used for decades in
cognitive neuroscience and
electrophysiology
that can be understood in terms of the
computational architecture
and message passing under simply
imperative
to minimize uncertainty about the way
the world works and indeed how i work in
that world this conclusion i think is
nicely summarized
in relation to eye movements by
helmholtz who was the
father of many of the uh um
inferential interpretations of the
scheme so each movement we make by which
we alter
the appearance of objects should be
thought of as an experiment designed to
test where they have understood
correctly
the invariant relationships in the
phenomenon of the forest that is their
existence in definite
spatial relations and with that opinion
remains
for me to thank the people whose ideas
might be talking about
but as well thank you for your attention
thank you very much
so to clarify something can we
return to your first example with the
oval
and so i have two questions related to
this first example the first one
is how in term of
how can you describe in your theory
the hungriness of the oh why
is that now and why the girl has
believed
that the prey should be catched it's the
first question
and another one is related and maybe
it's
how i'm trying to resolve this problem
is
the question is how is active
interventional influential selection
and because testing hypothesis is risky
it's time and energy consuming i mean
that you are resolving uncertainty you
invest something in
in terms of your energy and your time
and so on and what do you think about
how
natural selection shapes these prior
beliefs to make them
like more efficient in terms of survival
not only in terms of complete
so the first question how do i account
for
context specific drives you know what
determines the best sort of behavior
of even when i'm very hungry as opposed
to when i'm just
meeting so in this scheme
[Applause]
so here that would be a nice example of
having a hierarchical challenging
where your prior preferences will now
become conditioned upon different states
of people so if i were to and
now we're interested that we are
entering
the interesting world of acting
influence
applied to the homeless spaces and
spaces of interception
the last way i have involved creating
the next question
to have a genetic model under the brain
that was able to recognize that certain
states
so that these were good explanations
for particular gut feelings of a
particular
particular inputs from say receptors
measuring
your blood sugar and
also my beliefs about when i last
have something to eat then if i had
those representations i would be able to
do two things first of all
i would be able to contextualize my
prior preferences about what i think i
will be doing in half an hour which
could be
being in a restaurant or it could be
continuing to work or it could be
continuing to socialize
so you can contextualize any behavior
simply by conditioning a parameter
model at one level on both slowly
context
dependent states at the higher level if
you have a sufficiently deep project
and that leads to all sorts of
interesting issues you know the
distinction between
homeless spaces and other spaces and so
i would imagine that the virus unlike
the earth doesn't worry about whether
it's hungry or not people
just want let us take an e coli the
e coli doesn't worry about whether it's
hungry or not
it just consumes chemotactic gradients
and um
immediately minimizes uh it chooses
policies of a very trivial saw which is
just the very next thing to do
um based upon fixed price that never
changed the homeostatic standpoint
that's very different difficult having
another level above
which recognizes a different state
um that would then actually change the
satellite
at that point would be from a homostatic
reflex
to our spaces where we now start to
anticipate
the causes of our behavior for our
homeless places
so i will go and eat something before i
need to have a difficult
autonomic reflex until my very very
lower ones
so i think it is a great question
because what it speaks to
is about we're not dealing with simple
genetic variables
for a thermostat or a virus we're
dealing with very deeply
structured and i repeat diatronic in the
sense of separation and temporal time
spills
which are the kinds of models which
would be devastating
and possibly even the bacteria and then
the question
answer that by is your um third question
the model is just a price so
the price would be of a formal or a
structural sort
how many levels does my model have
so if you were doing machine learning
and
deep learning let's say using a
variational encoder
you have priorities when you say yes
there are 12 hidden layers
and hidden there 6 has 270
units you know all of these are formed
files and you believe
are fitting the purpose and appropriate
to the kind of data that you want
to classify and then of course you
actually have the
parametric prize the actual prior
expectations the inspirations and
everything that you would normally
associate with
so by model i need promise and
you know obviously there's an idea but
that's usually because the
likelihood just lives at the bottom
of these models so if we go to that
this graphic here all of these are
products
the only time becomes evident is right
at the bottom here
so all the interesting structure in
terms of its depth and
conditioning and contextualization is in
the prior structure
and the actual quantity of parametric
prize
you apply to all of these variables so
that brings you
me to you to your second question where
do they come from
and again you appeal to hierarchical
immigrants but now over
a more extended time frame so from the
point of view of statistician
the way that you would learn the good
prize
for a particular environment for a
particular sort of data
by monitoring learning for example or
structural learning
which used mainly modern selection so
now
you are selecting the form of those
models
that maximizes more importance for the
average sharing time
and if you look for the physiological
common likelihood of that it could be
things like
mindfulness i will be giving a lecture
that demonstrates that point towards the
end at some point this week so
uh opportunity to discuss this further
uh but probably more interesting i think
is
all of this takes place at an
evolutionary time scale
so the way that mathematically you bring
all of these things
um under the same principle
is to interpret natural selection as
bayesian model selection and that's
actually very easy to do
by not only that in the past 10 years
people have now started
to interpret in theoretical biology
the models or the dynamics of natural
selection
in terms of asian filtering so for
example
the replicated dynamics or the
replicator
or price equation these are
can be very easily shown to inspect with
abusive
simplified assumptions to they can be
shortly a bayesian filters or caliber
built
what you're saying is that
evolution is just nature's way of doing
amazing
selection to change or to select
those models those prior structures as
phenotypes
that have the greatest evidence what do
you mean by heavens
the likelihood that they are there i
hope that they are about to orange
for that environment so from the
environment point of view
it is testing the hypothesis that this
is a good thing for me
the environment or this phenotype or
this phenotype
and the evidence that it is a good fit
for me in the environment
corresponds to adaptive thickness you
scored
by the time interval of the variation of
the energy because that's the bandwidth
of the probability of that model
being the right model given the
experience provided by the environment
so the answer is it all comes down to
evolution it's exactly the same process
operating very very very slowly and in
that context you
wouldn't think about the phenotype as
being the individual
[Music]
is
is it possible in terms of your theory
to describe
just to describe and explain the huge
quality
difference between humans and other
animals
and he's there already maybe in that
presentation by the
theory and he
[Music]
because i think it speaks very much to
what we were just talking about
i think it's just the depth of the
german model
that distinguishes the kinds of
structures
that you associate with being you as
opposed to say a dog
as opposed to say a fish say
so just the district between single cell
organisms and
multicellular organisms it immediately
speaks to some
hierarchical aspect a nesting aspect
but if you take that further and just
think what's
what kinds of hierarchical extensions
would make you you as opposed to a
bacterium
or being mean as opposed to a bacterium
i think the answer is in this
depth in time i think that's basically
it i think
it almost reduces to the very simple
observation
that you and i plan and the bacteria
doesn't
and we can argue about when the being
deals your dog does
but certainly the bacterium
doing its chemotaxis does not count
it does not plan to go to school or to
buy birthday presents
whereas we do so what do you need to
plan
to plan this to select a month's various
policies
which means you have to have a genetic
problem in the future the consequences
of those pulses
so that's just simply a statement of the
fact that we
infer our world under generative models
that have a temporal depth
they have a horizon that goes beyond the
present
that enables us to plan and to think
about it
what would happen if i did that now
because as soon as you have that
capacity
you've now got to make a chance so the
bacteria doesn't have a choice about
what it does but you and i do
and i think that's of qualitative
distinction which again is just a
structural fire
is the thing that distinguishes higher
life from
lower life it's not the same
um you know for any particular economic
environment there will be a free energy
extreme
so viruses are great for fitting and
inferring their
video their environment which is usually
another person's cell
another cell we'd be very proud of that
i'd have to compress you down very very
small
you would not do very well inside a cell
but the virus will not do very well at
university
so it's all in relation to
um the way of your sensory inputs from
your environment
at that your time scale and once you
acknowledge that
that there are lots of global minima
that correspond to all sorts of
different ways of being both in terms of
species but also
humanized within the species then you
can see
now an easy taxology in terms of
hierarchal depth and sophistication
and particularly temporal depth that i
think comfortably
separates us from other animals
other animals from planets
thank you very
uh i much like to put it like a little
bit away from let me say
a scientific point of view towards a big
kind of uh
theoretical future prediction whatever
do you think it is possible
first question uh to fit a current state
of psychological outlooks
towards uh personal belief motivations
and beliefs into the scheme that you're
describing like
saying that those uh beliefs that are
like
wrongly you know into the person and
they could also
be kind of hidden states for the person
which is not recognizing
um and if so
is the responsibility your point of view
to create
like a maybe backed software
which will be impossible to predict um
uh behavior of each kind of like certain
person in certain conditions
like i've given kind of enormous power
outside you know something
i'll just um a practical one um
and take your question as a psychiatrist
because then it becomes very important
in terms of understanding
made beliefs of false beliefs and the
remediation
of that false influence that may or may
not be
a good thing or a bad thing but
certainly being able to do it and
understand what you're doing
is practically very relevant confidence
could be psychology or it could be
marching by drugs
so the idea here is that um
most psychiatric syndromes can be
thought of
as a form of false or
buried influence so a lucillation
would be basically believing a person
that something is there when there's an
ancestry evidence for it and illusion
is having a conviction in some state of
affairs
usually interpersonal for which there is
no
evidence that a normal person would
accept us attendance foreign
things like anorexia and disorder phobia
holding beliefs about myself which
have no evidence when i look at myself
in a miracle
i see myself as fat quite a scene by the
third
that i am flat even when you kind of see
things very
very thin so you can certainly get an
enormous variety
of posterior deletes i'd say that like a
constable you could
bring them to a certain number of fears
like
death hunger whatever just i mean that's
why i'm asking so those i believe are
not
uncountable to me there can be brought
to like
maybe but still a final number of
countable factors you know yes
uh there will be mathematical reasons
for competition
um so if that's the case if there is an
opportunity
there's political evidence for a parent
relief
updating then you
people have been focusing on how that
could happen
and it seems that the most important
synaptic mechanism that enables that
sort of false inference
is in the precision afforded to various
sources of sensory evidence relative to
priorities
so if you're a psychologist you you
think of that in terms of retention
so now the game becomes shifting from
how we form our beliefs
update our beliefs to how we attend to
different things and we were talking
just before about
big data but the real problem is is to
select
what you accredit or assign
a position that enable that
enables that sort of information to
update your beliefs
so i think in terms of understanding the
mechanics of relief updating
and intervening in that kind of
therapeutically more for
commercial reasons i think advertising
for example
it's probably going to be all about how
you manipulate attention
and what you mean by attention and the
physiological mechanism
mechanisms of protection and also
just gaining some high level control of
attention to be able to mentalize
suppression so this is the phenomenon
when i move my eyes as i
look around the room during the motion
of the eyes i do not see the object
i don't see the world's sweet person all
i see
are the static samples that i then
integrate
into a coherent theme so that
circadic suppression is a very
interesting example
of temporarily ignoring or reducing the
precision
of the likelihood mapping here in a very
very um temporally precise way
which you cannot affect five at least
higher
in the world now imagine that you now
had a connection
in the genetic model so you had
you felt hard reason to talk about
contextualizing before
saying some higher level representation
myself or myself state itself at this
point in time
you can actually now then
suspend that surcharge oppression so you
could choose whether to see
the world really when you move your eyes
or not if you have to
say you can
so there are ways of getting around it
if you have a sufficiently
deep degenerative model so
just in terms of practically what you
would be looking at i think you'll be
looking at the processes
the media and the precision and the
degree of message opacity between these
hierarchical levels
that would look very much like what you
treat us and use
if you get foreign of that for yourself
and possible for a patient that you you
may well have an enormous therapy
thank you i wasn't talking like exactly
about therapeutic
affects like protein association
system which is still being bad
you know so can you give me a call
um
well it is same thing um like as you
said
advertisement right so it's not like
kind of like changing human attitudes
explaining that facts are bad or
whatever
you know uh not hypnotized that's right
but they just
predict what kind of uh
disorder will react to this kind of like
what will be the way that people with
these or that kind of disorder not
psychiatric
like that like uh epithelial level you
know
um to this certain message uh like the
behavior non-humanized paths of that so
the builders still die
will they still like will they say no
will they say yes
i'm talking about kind of a
prognostication model not like
improvement but just improvement of the
management not improvement of your
agents themselves
[Music]
this particular mathematical formulation
hasn't really gone that far
it's penetrated theoretical biology in
terms of multi-ancient games
um construction and mythology so there
are simulations of
how multiple agents you can each
construct and
constrain
simulations at the level of cells
organizing different patterns and
coalitions
but nobody to my knowledge has taken
these
variational free energy solutions
and to model markets of advertising or
geopolitical events that provides a
really exciting opportunity but to my
knowledge
it hasn't been done it's only been
initially invested in the past couple of
years
in mythology and in uh revolutionary
psychology
and in the world genesis
well thank you very much for an
interesting presentation
i would like to ask several questions
concerning our mark of
our processes uh first of all
the principal feature called market
processes
is that the future is determined
by the past only while present
is this fact resulted from the
application
or it's only their simplification to be
able to solve mathematical
problems associated with
problem-solving the second question is
on this slide we would do
uh there is two magnitudes uh entropy
and energy entropy is non-dimensional
[Music]
energy
so can i ask you as a physicist um so
a really interesting question first of
all you get to what extent um
are the markovian independences or um
markovian process assumptions implicit
in the markup decision process
do we think what is one thing that these
are
the only kinds of genetic models that
are fit for
the universe in which we live i think
technically um all of this
maths inherits from the
treatment of random developmental
systems
castle is a large vibrant system in
which case the markovian properties
would be true and fundamental that's
where you start
so um my answer would be
they are not a device of that matter of
convenience
they are actually baked in to the
underlying premise
[Applause]
and that also enables me to um address
the third question
um what we are basically solving here
are not ordinary differential equations
that would follow from a stochastic
differential equation that you can treat
and launch our performance paths they
could be applied to the density delays
for example
uh equation on the density dynamics of a
strong wave equation or a master
equation
so much of this really all of these
simulations are actually
up to great intercepts on functions
where there's a function of probability
distribution
very much like uh the vodka plank
equation so that's
the belief aspect that we're moving away
from gradient flows on functions and
states of
gradient flows and path functions of
states
but interpreting them now in terms of
great inflows that are functionals of
beliefs and coding by states
it's a big technical review if you'd
like to discuss that further in email
i'll send you
something never dead
that takes you through those arguments
uh very precisely
um the interesting thing um
though is is the coming back to the
first
question because clearly
this particular mdp
is semi-markovian i have broken the
markovian property
because i've now got two time scales in
place here
so in practice what happens with
these immensely complicated itinerant
attracting sex that we
use as the mathematical model of
self-organizing systems like biological
systems
when you summarize it in terms of a
markovian-like process with a discrete
uh in speech states and in speed time
it looks like it has now acquired a
semiconductor
aspect so it is interesting that from
the purely markovian physics of it
due to the complicated nature of the
systems that we
like to study when you find
the free energy optimizing models
they turn out to be hierarchical with
that briefing the civil market to make
the decision
so at that point i think that the
discrete
monarch decision process does become a
mathematical approximation
to what is actually a continuous time
markovian process
that looks as if it's lost its uh simple
markovian property
because it's just become so active so
complicated
so structured and so interesting from a
biological
perspective is that a reasonable answer
yes
you